Benjamin Franklin Papers Part 12 -- Letters from Franklin 1733-1789 Mss.B.F85inventory12
American Philosophical Society
- Letters from Benjamin Franklin
  - to [John] Huske., 1772 September 6; A. Dr. of L.S. 1p.; Franklin, Benjamin. London
    America is obliged to him for his continued good wishes and schemes; the obtaining money from the poor treasury to forward such schemes, although beneficial to America, is out of all expectation. A new colony is forming where good land may be had cheap.
    Printed in Works (Smyth, V, 435).
  - to [John] Walsh., 1772 September 6; A. Dr. of L.S. 1p.; Franklin, Benjamin. London
    Glad that he intends publishing an account of his experiments. Dr. [Joseph] Pricstlcy found that growing vegetables restore air that has been spoilt by putrefaction.
    Printed in Works (Smyth, V, 436).
  - to Dr. Cadwalader Evans, Philadelphia., 1772 December 2; A.L.S. 1p.; Franklin, Benjamin. London
    Is much concerned to hear of his illness. Has received his favor of October 21st, with bill drawn by order of the Managers for Promoting the Culture of Silk, and is glad the purchase he made was satisfactory. As the sum exceeds his disbursement the overplus will wait his orders. The truss was sent, is vexed that it did not came to hand, and must inquire what became of it.
  - to [Barbeu] Dubourg., 1772 December 26; A. Dr. of L.S. 2p.; Benjamin, Franklin. London
    Spelling. Will enquire of Messrs. Dilly for the American [Philosohical Society's] Transactions.
    Printed in Works (Smyth, V, 463).
  - to Madame A-------., [1772.]; A. Dr. of L.S. 1p.; Benjamin, Franklin
    Informs her that there is no grant of land as yet to be obtained from those concerned in the new colony, their grant from the Crown not having yet passed the Seals. Thinks with so many children she will be better in Pennsylvania than in London; the children can be got into sober, industrious families and taught a trade on much easier terms than in London. Mr. A ---'s dexterity in business may induce his being engaged in some store. Thinks Mrs. A--- could open a boarding school for girls. Refers her to Mr. and Mrs. [Richard] Bache.
  - to [Barbeu] Dubourg., [1772.]; A.L.S. 1p.; Franklin, Benjamin
    Acknowledges receipt of package containing two parcels of the Ephemerides. Sends salutations of Madame Dubourg, Mille. Bihéron and other friends. Promises himself the happiness of seeing, them and him once more, for he thinks of returning home (when he does return) through France and Italy, taking his passage at Leghorn in some of the ships that go thither with corn or fish.
  - Directions for Discovering Whether the Power that gives the Shock in Touching the Torpedo or the Gymnotus of Surinam is Electrical or not., [1772.]; A. Dr. Mem. 1p.; Benjamin, Franklin
    Printed in Works (Sparks, V, 412; Bigelow, III, 466; Symth, V. 539).
  - to ----- ------., 1772 (?); A. Dr. of L.S. 4p.; Franklin, Benjamin
    Relative to the use of pointed conductors in Philadelphia and London to secure buildings from lightning. Pointed conductors for the magazines of gunpowder at Purfleet. Hopes he removed the prejudice of his fellow-citizens relating to his conductor, and that he has since completed it, so as to make the experiment with it, he had in view.
  - to ----- -----., A. Mem. 2p.; Franklin, Benjamin, 1706-1790
    Questions relating to Ireland.
  - New Version of the Lord's Prayer., [1772.]; 3p.; Franklin, Benjamin, 1706-1790
    Giving reasons for the proposed changes in expression.
    (A. Dr. of Diss. In Duplicate.)
    Printed in Works (Sparks, I, 77; Smyth, VII, 427).
  - to Sir William Browne., [1772.]; A.L.S. "An Offended Fellow of the R[oyal] Society."; Franklin, Benjamin, 1706-1790
    Warning against any further publication of malicious libels and forged articles.
  - to Sir J[ohn] Pringle., [Circa 1772.]; A. Dr. of L. in 3d P. 1p.; Franklin, Benjamin, 1706-1790
    Is greatly obliged for the trouble he took in the affair of the silk and is happy to hear that the Queen condescended to accept it with a purpose of wearing it. This will afford the silk raisers of Pennsylvania great encouragement to proceed in a measure the British Parliament seems to have had much at heart, the procnring a supply of that valuable article from the Colonies, for which large sums are paid yeartly to France, Spain, Italy and the Indies.
  - to Barbeu Dubourg., [1772?]; A. Dr. of L. 2p.; Franklin, Benjamin, 1706-1790
    Does not think damp clothes caues colds any more than wet clothes. The securing of fruits from the mischief of frosts. (Incomplete. Mutilated.)
  - to [Mrs. Deborah Franklin]., 1773 January 6; A.L.S. 1p.; Franklin, Benjamin. London
    His birthday. Glad she continues well.
    Printed in Works (Sparks, VIII, 31; Bigelow, V, 86; Smyth, VI, 4).
  - to Mrs. [Deborah] Franklin. Philadelphia., 1773 March 15; A.L.S. 1p.; Franklin, Benjamin. London
    Sends her a box containing sundry parcels for his friends, and silk and gowns for her Sally [Franklin]. Continues well and hopes soon to see her and home.
  - to [Jean Baptiste] Le Roy., [1773.] March 30; A. Dr. of L.S. 1p.; Franklin, Benjamin. London
    Pointed conductors for the public magazines of gunpowder, and their disadvantages as claimed by Mr. [Benjamin] Wilson in his pamphlet to alarm the people of their danger. Sent a volume of American [Philosophical Society's] Transactions to the Academy of Sciences in Paris and when he found it was favorably recived, he acquaints him, he nominated him a member of that Society and he was elected January 15. Two ships are being fitted out by the Admiralty at the request of the Royal society to make a voyage to the North Pole.
    Printed in works (Bigelow, V, 120; Smyth, VI, 28).
  - to Mrs. [Deborah] Franklin, Philadelphia., 1773 April 6; A.L.S. 1p.; Franklin, Benjamin. London
    Did all he could to serve Mrs. [Patience] Wright, but somehow or other he displeased her of late and she does not now come near him. Condoles with her on the loss of their friend Mr. David Hall. His old friends so drop off that he is afraid, when he comes home, he will find himself a stranger in his own country. Is pleased with the accounts of her kingbird [Benjamin Franklin Bache]. Mrs. [Margaret] Stevenson and Polly send their love, Sally her duty, she is to be married and leave us next week.
  - to Dean [Richard] Woodward., 1773 April 10; A. Dr. of L.S. 1p.; Franklin, Benjamin. London
    Possibility of abolishing slavery in America. Influence of the English merchants with the Government. Ships transporting convicts to America.
    Printed in Works (Sparks, VIII, 42; Bigelow, V, 128; Smyth, VI, 39).
  - to William Deane., 1773 April 11; A. Dr. of L.S. 2p.; Franklin, Benjamin. London
    A new carriage wheel. Heard that some person has discovered a new moving power; asks him if he knows anything of the application of this power. Has completed his stove which consumes its own smoke.
    Printed in Works (Sparks, VI, 383; Bigelow, V, 129; Smyth, VI, 40).
  - to [Barbeu] Dubourg., 1773 May 28; A. Dr. of L.S. 4p.; Franklin, Benjamin. London
    Will forward what remarks he has made when he finishes examining the rest of the sheets. Is obliged to him for proposing to insert the letter as written from Dubourg to Franklin. Remarks on the papers relating to the powder magazine. Wishes that some chemist with a knowledge of electricity, would work on glass with Dubourg's views, this would prevent misunderstandings and contradictory sentiments when the same experiments are performed by different persons. Cause for the breaking of the glass bottles when highly charged in the Leyden experiment. His globe, that could not be excited, is of a different composition from the other glass. Dubourg's Para Tonnerre. (Incomplete.)
  - to [Jean Baptiste] Le Roy., 1773 June 22; A. Dr. of L.S. 1p.; Franklin, Benjamin. London
    Hospitals. Effect of fresh air on diseases.
    Printed in Works (Sparks, VI, 385; Bigelow, V, 151, Smyth, VI, 59).
  - to M. [Jean] Rozier., 1773 June 22; A. Dr. of L.S. 1p.; Franklin, Benjamin. London
    Thanks him for his polite letter and the present of his valuable collection. Has purchased of M. Magalhaens [John Hyacinth Magellan] all the numbers of small form. Thinks it must prove a useful work in science and wishes it success.
  - to [Barbeu] Dubourg., 1773 June 29; A. Dr. of L.S. 2p.; Franklin, Benjamin. London
    A list of errata in the French translation of the Works of Franklin. The causes of taking cold.
    Printed, in part, in Works (Sparks,VI, 387; Bigelow, V, 153; Smyth, VI, 61).
  - to Dr. [Matthew] Maty., 1773 July 1; A. Dr. of L.S. 1p.; Franklin, Benjamin. London
    Mr. [John] Walsh intended to draw up an account of the numerous experiments on the torpedo, but his other avocation has not permitted him to execute it. Has lately received permission to lay before the [Royal] Society what Mr. [John] Walsh had communicated to him.
    Printed in Works (Smyth, VI, 72).
  - to Mrs. [Deborah] Franklin, Philadelphia., 1773 July 15; A.L.S. 1p.; Franklin, Benjamin. London
    Account of articles he sends her. Congratulates her on Sally [Bache]'s safe delivery of another son, hopes he proves another pleasure to her.
  - to [Jonathan Shipley], The Lord Bishop of St. Asaph., 1773 August 21; A. Dr. of L.S. 1p.; Franklin, Benjamin. London
    Sends him a Boston newspaper in which his sermon is advertised. His sermon is universally received with great approbation and wonder. The Speaker of the Massachusetts Assembly says it is much liked, as it discovers a Catholic spirit and sentiments very favorable in regard to America.
  - to ---- Burdett., 1773 August 21; A. Dr. of L.S. 2p.; Franklin, Benjamin. London
    Thinks he would be a great acquisition to the Colonies if he could remove there, but doubts the Colonies being able to bear the expense. Would be glad to be informed where he could see some samples of printing in imitation of painting.
    Printed in Works (Smyth, VI, 113).
  - to [John Cuthbert]., 1773 August 28; A. Dr. of L.S. 1p.; Franklin, Benjamin. London
    Received and sent the coal-mine drawings to France; hopes they are not too late to be use to M. [Jean François Clément] Morand, who, in despair of receiving them, thought of publishing his book without them.
  - to Mrs. [Deborah] Franklin, Philadelphia., 1773 September 1; A.L.S. 2p.; Franklin, Benjamin. London
    Death of Dr. [Cadwalader] Evans. Fears that when he returns home, he will find himself a stranger. Her god-daughter Amelia Evans, who was married to a Capt. Barry of a ship in the Turkish trade, returned from Africa; Mrs. [Margaret] Stevenson and he dined with her and her husband. Mrs. Barry's children. A new translation of his book, being the thrid edition in French; to this a print of him has been prefixed which has so French a countenance that she would take him for one of that lively nation.
    Printed, in part, in Works (Sparks, VIII, 117; Bigelow, V, 213; Smyth, VI, 118)
  - [John] Baskerville., 1773 September 21; A. Dr. of L.S. 2p.; Franklin, Benjamin. London
    Sale of printers' types. Sheet of Chinese paper. Asks him whether he should purchase any matrices for him from Rumford and James's foundries.
    Printed in Works (Sparks, VIII, 87; Bigelow, V, 222; Smyth, VI, 125).
  - to [Thomas Percival]., 1773 September 25; A. Dr. of L.S. 2p.; Franklin, Benjamin. West Wycombe, Seat of Lord le Despencer
    Benefits and manner of taking the census every year in China. The amazing number of deaths in Manchester due to the unwholesomeness of the manufacturing life. Moist air not unwholesome. Healthiness of the inhabitants of Bermuda, St. Helena, etc.
    Printed in Works (Sparks, VI, 402; Bigelow, V, 235; Smyth, VI, 138).
  - to Dr. [J.] Ingenhousz., 1773 September 30; A. Dr. of L.S. 2p.; Franklin, Benjamin. London
    Hopes to leave England next May or June. Sri W[illiam] Hamilton writes from Naples that he has not been able to perceive any certain signs of electricity in the torpedo. Magnetic needle. Nairne's electric machine. Electric rods for the powder magazine at Purfleet. Mr. [Benjamin] Wilson objects to pointed rods. Received a spy glass from M. Tremont, an ingenious young Italian.
    Printed in Works (Sparks, VI, 406; Bigelow, V, 237; Smyth, VI, 141).
  - to [Henry Sampson] Woodfall., [1773 September ?]; A.L. in 3d P. 1p.; Franklin, Benjamin, 1706-1790
    If he should think fit to give the enclosed [Rules for Reducing a Great Empire] a place in his paper, he should take care that the compositor observes strictly the italicizing, capitalizing and the pointing. Requests him to let the enclosed appear in the P[ublic] A[dvertiser] as soon as he can, conveniently. [It appeared in October, 1773.]
  - to The Public Advertiser., [1773. September.]; A. Dr. of L. 3p.; Franklin, Benjamin, 1706-1790
    Rules by which a great empire may be reduced to a small one.(Incomplete.)
    Printed in The Public Advertiser, Oct. 1773, also as a pamphlet, 16 p., 8 vo., London, 1793, and in Works (Sparks, IV, 387; Bigelow, V, 223; Smyth, VI, 127).
  - to Mrs. [Deborah] Franklin, Philadelphia., 1773 October 6; A.L.S. 1p.; Franklin, Benjamin. London
    Must stay another winter in England, but nothing shall prevent his return in the spring. His health continues but cannot expect it much longer, which makes him the more anxious to be where he would choose to die. Mrs. [Margaret] Stevenson's grandchildren.
  - to ------ ------., 1773 October 13; A. Dr. of L.S. 1p.; Franklin, Benjamin. London
    Relative to the marriage with one's deceased wife's sister. Can see no political or moral objection to it.
  - to [--------, an Engraver]., 1773 November 3; Dr. of L.S. 2p. (Copy); Franklin, Benjamin. London
    Art of engraving on chinaware. Will not contest the honor for the copper-plate engravings for earthenware. Use of the art in teaching moral lessons. Mr. [Joseph] Banks is preparing to publish the Botanical Discoveries of his voyage.
    Printed in Works (Sparks, VIII, 94; Bigelow, V, 249; Smyth, VI, 149).
  - to -------- ------., [Circa 1773.]; A.Dr. of L.S. 3p.; Franklin, Benjamin, 1706-1790
    Relative to the cure of rhcumatism by electricity.
  - to Lord Morton., 1767 Nov 19-24; A. Dr. of L.S. 1p.; Franklin, Benjamin, 1706-1790
    Looked over that part of Dr. [Joseph] Priestley's work containing an account of his experiments and found a great number of them, mostly quite new, some very curious and important, and therefore well deserving the honor of the [Royal] Society's [Copley?] medal.
  - to ------- ------., 1773; A.Dr. of L. 1p.; Franklin, Benjamin. London
    States what should be done with writers who try to widen the breach between the Colonies or with those who are nurtured in revolutionary principles.
  - Advertisement., 1773; A.Mem. 2p.; Franklin, Benjamin, 1706-1790
    Relating to the choice of proper Psalms. Written for the "Abridgment of the Book of Common Prayer."
  - Preface to the Abridgment of the Book of Common Prayer., 1773; A. Diss. 4p.; Franklin, Benjamin, 1706-1790
    Printed in Works (Sparks, X, 207, Note; Bigelow, V, 274; Smyth, VI, 165).
  - Memorandum., 1773; A. Mem. 1p.; Franklin, Benjamin, 1706-1790
    Note in the "Abridgment of the Book of Common Prayer" under the first page of the catechism, that it is not so well adapted to the capacitics of children as might be wished and therefore only those plain answers which express their duty towards God and their neighbors are retained.
    Printed in Works (Sparks, X, 211, Note, first paragraph; Bigelow, V, 279, last paragraph, Smyth, VI, 170, Second paragraph).
  - to The Royal Society., [1773.]; A. Dr. of L. 4p.; Franklin, Benjamin, 1706-1790
    Relative to the Committee's report on pointed conductors for the magazines at Purfleet. Mr. [Benjamin] Wilson's criticism. Advantages of the pointed rods. Conditions under which pointed rods are not essential. (Incomplete.)
  - to Barbeu Dubourg., 1773 ?; A. Dr. of L. 3p.; Franklin, Benjamin, 1706-1790
    Corrections of a text on electricity.
  - to The Editor of ------., 1773; A. Dr. of L. 1p.; Franklin, Benjamin, 1706-1790
    As the bare letters of a Governor of one of the Provinces, accusing the people of rebellious intentions is looked upon as sufficient ground for inflicting penalties on such Provinces, without hearing anything from the defense, he requests him to give to the public the extract of the pamphlet which was written at the time of their last year's disputes, by one who lived long in America, knew the people and their affairs very well.
  - to ----- -----., [1773.]; A. Dr. of L. 1p.; Franklin, Benjamin, 1706-1790
    Relative to the power of the Crown to make void laws presented for its approval. (Incomplete.)
  - to [Richard] Bache., 1774 February 17; A. Dr. of L.S. 1p.; Franklin, Benjamin. London
    Has been displaced from office. Proposes to return home next May. Sends a number of boxes of printing letters which he purchased exceedingly cheap.
    Printed in Works (Smyth, VI, 193).
  - to [Joseph] Galloway., 1774 February 18; A. Dr. of L.S. 2p.; Franklin, Benjamin. London
    Acts of the Pennsylvania Assembly. Duty on tea. Hutchinson letters. Indecent treatment he received at the hands of the Privy Council. Wishes a Constitution was formed and settled for America.
    Printed in part, in Works (Sparks, VIII, 115; Bigelow, V, 314; in full, Smyth, VI, 194).
  - to Tho[ma]s Foxcroft., 1774 February 18; A. Dr. of L.S. 1p.; Franklin, Benjamin. London
    Received his account. Thanks him for ordering the six barrels of flour. Tea ship arrived having a very short passage. Wrote to his family to receive no more payments, being displaced from office.
  - to Rich[ar]d Nicholls Colden, Esq., 1774 February 18; A. Dr. of L.S. 1p.; Benjamin Franklin. London
    Received his bills and has given credit for them to the General Post Office; begs that the account may be sent punctuaily that he may settle them before he leaves England, which is now necessary as he is no longer in office.
  - to J[ames] Kinsey and T.P. Hewlings, Burlington., 1774 February 18; A. Dr. of L.S. 1p.; Franklin, Benjamin. London
    Sends them the Act for settling their boundary between their Province and New York. The obstruction in America to the importation of tea has occasioned great resentment; violent measures are apprehended. Sends his respects to the Assembly.
  - to R[obert] Strettel Jones and Josiah Hewes., 1774 February 18; A. Dr. of L.S. 1p.; Franklin, Benjamin. London
    Received their letter and immediately ordered the books. The new edition of the Encyclopedia may be excepted in about two years. Received the catalogue. Glad the Library [Company of Philadelphia] is satisfactorily situated.
  - to Abel James and Benjamin Morgan., 1774 February 18; A. Dr. of L.S. 1p.; Franklin, Benjamin. London
    Accepted the draft and will duly pay it. Happy to find that his small services have been acceptable to the Society [for promoting the Culture of Silk].
  - to [John] Foxcroft., 1774 February 18; A. Dr. of L.S. 1p.; Franklin, Benjamin. London
    Hopes nothing he has written has occasioned any coolness. Although no longer colleagues, he begs that they part in friendship. Displaced unwillingly by his masters who were obliged to comply with the orders of the Ministry. Proposes coming home next May.
    Printed in Works (Smyth, VI, 197).
  - to [Edward] Antill., 1774 February 18; A. Dr. of L.S. 1p.; Franklin, Benjamin. London
    Was displaced from office before he had an opportunity of answering his letter, which puts it out of his power to do him any service in what he proposed; will speak to Mr. [Henry] Potts concerning his letter and acquaint him with the result.
  - to Marquis de Condorcet., 1774 March 20; A. Dr. of L.S. 2p.; Franklin, Benjamin. London
    Answer his questions about America.
    Printed in Wroks (Sparks, VI, 411; Biglow, V, 341; Smyth. VI, 221).
  - to Père [Giambatista] Beccaria., 1774 March 20; A. Dr. of L. 1p.; Franklin, Benjamin. London
    Mr. [John] Walsh discovered that vacuum resists the passage of the electric fluid. (Incomplete.)
    Printed in Works (in part Sparks, VI, 413; Bigelow, V, 343; entire letter, Smyth, VI, 225).
  - to Mrs. [Deborah] Franklin, Philadelphia., 1774 May 5; A.L.S. 1p.; Franklin, Benjamin. London
    His family in England is in great distress. Mrs. [Mary] Hewson has lost her husband and Mrs. [Margaret] Stevenson her son-in-law. Distress of the family.
  - to Thomas Cushing, 1774 June 1; A. Dr. of L.S. 2p.; Franklin, Benjamin. London
    Massachusetts affairs. Lord Chatham blamed the Americans for destroying the tea, but condemns the measures taken in Parliament in consequence thereof. Is obliged to remain in England a little longer. Has been displaced from office.
    Printed in Works (Sparks, VIII, 122; Bigelow, V, 354; Smyth, VI, 231).
  - to Tho[ma]s Cushing., 1774 June 30; A. Dr. of L. 1p.; Franklin, Benjamin. London
    Will send him all the perfected Acts lately passed relating to the Province. Sends copies of two more letters of Mr. Hutchinson. The Chancery suit goes on against him.
    Printed in Works (Bigelow, V, 356).
  - to Dr. [Benjamin] Rush., 1774 July 22; A. Dr. of L.S. 3p.; Franklin, Benjamin. London
    Thought it best to postpone Dr. Rush's publication until after his election to the [Royal] Society; should the article be published before his election, Dr. Franklin fears it might prejudice some votes against him. Dr. North's apparatus for the making of Pyrmont water.
    Printed, in part, in Works (Smyth, VI, 235).
  - to The Rev. [Thomas] Coombe., 1774 July 22; A. Dr. of L.S. 1p.; Franklin, Benjamin. London
    Bishop of St. Asaph's speech. Sends him the "Heroic Postscript," a poem, the author of which is unknown. Use of eloquence in a preacher.
    Printed in Works (Sparks, VIII, 124; Bigelow, V, 356; Smyth, VI, 233).
  - to Mr. [Richard] Bache., 1774 July 22; A.Dr. of L.S. 1p.; Franklin, Benjamin. London
    Has had no line from him. Capt. [Nathaniel] Falconer put the casks of type in his cellar, not knowing for whom they were; asks him to get them and store them with the rest.
  - to [Mrs. Deborah Franklin]., 1774 July 22; A. Dr. of L.S. 1p.; Franklin, Benjamin. London
    Has not received a line from her, but flatters himself it is not owing to indisposition. Mrs. [Amelia] Barry, daughter of Lewis Evans, and Mrs. Franklin's god-daughter, who married the Captain of a ship in the Levant trade, is now again at Turnis, where she has lately lain-in of her third child. Her father was geographer, and his daughter has now some connection with the whole globe; being born herself in America and having her first child in Asia, her second in Europe, and now her third in Africa.
    Printed in Works (Sparks, VIII, 125; Bigelow,V, 358; Smyth, VI, 234).
  - to [William Franklin], 1774 September 7; A. Dr. of L.S. 2p.; Franklin, Benjamin. London
    Decided to stay in England until he learns the result of the first Congress. Thinks the Bostonians ought not to pay for the tea that was destroyed. Death of Sir W[illiam] Johnson. Asks him to request Mr. [James] Kinsey to acknowledge to Mr. [James] Parker, the receipt of the Boundary Act. A Spanish war is seriously apprehended.
    Printed in Works (Sparks, VIII, 130; Bigelow, V, 359; Smyth, VI, 239).
  - to James Parker., 1774 September 7; A. Dr. of L.S. 1p.; Franklin, Benjamin. London
    Informs him he was directed by letter from Messrs. Kinsey and Hewlings to solicit the Royal confirmation of the Act for the establishment of the division line [between New Jersey and New York]. Sent those gentlemen authenticated copies. Will obtain a copy for Mr. [James] Parker should be deem it necessary, although the expense is very large.
  - to [Joseph] Galloway., 1774 September 7; A. Dr. of L.S. 1p.; Franklin, Benjamin. London